There are lots of good reasons
to try and follow a healthier diet—
you lose weight,
you feel good,
but the main reason?
To live a longer, happier,
more productive life.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Back by popular demand,
it’s the NutritionFacts Grab Bag,
where we look at the latest science
on a whole variety of topics.
And we start with Ginkgo Biloba.
Turns out it doesn’t seem to have any effect in
preventing cognitive decline or dementia.
But it may play a role in treating it.
More than a third
of older Americans
take some kind
of brain health supplement
to the tune
of billions of dollars a year,
and one of the most popular
is ginkgo biloba.
U.S. household surveys suggest
as many as 2 percent
of Americans
are taking gingko supplements.
Ginkgo biloba's a tree
with fan-shaped leaves,
regarded as a living fossil,
having persisted
relatively unchanged
for over
a quarter billion years.
Its resilience makes it
a favorite of urban planners,
hardy enough to survive
even a nuclear blast,
as one of the few survivors
within a short radius
of ground zero in Hiroshima.
Over the last 30 years or so,
an extract of gingko leaves
has become one of the most
widely used herbal treatments
for dementia.
A 2009 Cochrane review
of three dozen
randomized controlled trials
involving more than
4,000 participants
concluded that
the "evidence that ginkgo biloba
has predictable and clinically
significant benefit
for people with dementia
or cognitive impairment
is inconsistent
and unreliable."
One trial showed
very large benefits,
but others showed
no effect at all.
To put the subject to rest
once and for all,
two large randomized,
double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials
were conducted, one in Europe,
funded by a gingko
supplement manufacturer,
and the largest,
longest study to date,
funded by the NIH
in the United States.
More than 5,000
older men and women
with either normal cognition
or mild cognitive impairment
were randomized to
a gingko leaf extract or placebo
for five or six years
to see if it would prevent them
from sliding into dementia.
Mild cognitive impairment
is the intermediate
clinical state
between normal cognition
for one's age and dementia.
The conversion rate
of MCI to dementia
is about 10 percent per year.
The bottom line?
Neither trial
showed any clear benefit,
definitively demonstrating
no preventative effect.
However, for those
already suffering with dementia,
gingko leaf extracts do appear
to slow cognitive decline
compared to placebo
for those with Alzheimer's,
or dementia
more broadly defined.
Of course that's assuming
there's actually gingko
in your gingko supplements.
Investigations
of gingko supplements
off the shelves
in both Europe and the U.S.
found some that had
no apparent gingko at all.
As high as about
one in six ginkgo supplements
appeared to be all filler,
without any detectable
ginkgo biloba DNA.
Side-effects-wise,
at typical doses,
such as 120 mg twice a day,
ginkgo extracts may cause
mild stomach upset,
headache, dizziness,
constipation,
and allergic skin reactions.
Higher dosages can result
in restlessness, diarrhea,
nausea, vomiting, and weakness.
There have been about a dozen
published case reports
of bleeding
associated with gingko,
but thankfully
this did not surface
in systematic reviews
of the dementia studies.
Still, out of
an abundance of caution,
it's been recommended to
stop taking gingko supplements
at least two weeks
before elective surgery.
The bottom line,
according to a recent review
of Alzheimer's disease
therapies,
is that ginkgo
is one of the few things
that can beat out placebo
for cognitive function.
In our next story,
we look at Is the higher rate of
bladder cancer among hairdressers.
And we ask: is it due to
exposure to hair dyes?
And what about at-home
use of hair colorants?
Since there's typically no way
to reverse hair color loss,
the use of hair colorants
is a mainstay of management,
a practice documented
as far back as 1500 BCE.
While gray hair may carry
a distinguished look
and limit women's subjection
to a sexualized gaze,
hair color constitutes
a multibillion-dollar market
with up to 60 percent
of men and women
in Western countries choosing
to use coloring products,
many of which to cover gray.
For over a century,
aromatic amines
have been
the main chemicals used
in commercial permanent,
oxidative hair dyes.
The primary problem
with these compounds
is that they can be
potent contact allergens.
Product labels often recommend
a small 48-hour test application
to the skin before use,
but it can take up to a week
for a skin allergy to flare up.
They also may cause cancer.
Hair products contain
more than 5,000 chemicals,
and so it's hard
to narrow it down,
but the aromatic amines,
such as para-phenylenediamine,
that are often used in hair dyes
to prevent fading
due to washing,
have been picked out
as a "probable carcinogen."
Before industry reformulation
in response to
mandated cancer warning labels,
9 out of 10 permanent
hair dye products
were mutagenic,
meaning capable
of causing DNA mutations.
This then appeared to translate
into more than ten times
the odds of DNA damage
in breast cells
obtained from
the breast milk of women
who had used hair dye
in the last six months,
compared to
not using hair dyes at all.
But does it translate
into more cancer?
A meta-analysis of 42 studies
found that hairdressers,
particularly those
who held their jobs
10 or more years, were at
significantly higher risk
of developing bladder cancer
later in life.
Hairdressers, beauticians,
and barbers
may also suffer
more lung cancer,
voice box cancer,
and multiple myeloma.
There is some evidence that
hairdressers may smoke more,
but the researchers
took this into account.
They conclude that salons
should be better ventilated,
that gloves should be used.
But how much is that
going to help the person
whose head
has been soaked in it?
Based on testing
for radioactively-traced
hair dye ingredients
in the urine,
experiments suggest that
exposure to hair dye
may be
several hundred-fold higher
in hair dye users
than the occupational risk
to the hairdressers.
But thankfully there does not
seem to be an excess risk
of bladder cancer
among those who just
use hair dye personally.
Furthermore, major changes
took place in the 1980s
to make hair dyes safer.
In 1979, the U.S.
Food and Drug Administration
started requiring
cancer warning labels
on hair dye products,
leading the industry to start
reformulating to eliminate
the most carcinogenic
ingredients.
A turning point
in bladder cancer risk
isn't apparent from the data,
but this may just be a function
of the long latency time
between exposure and malignancy
for bladder cancer,
which can be 30 or 40 years.
If you look at
faster developing cancers,
such as leukemia
or follicular lymphoma,
there does seem to be
a drop-off in risk after 1980,
though a 2019 meta-analysis,
looking at
increased
non-Hodgkin's lymphoma risk
without consideration
of date range,
concluded "exposure to hair
colorants should be reduced
as much as possible."
For prostate cancer,
the doubling of odds
associated with hair dye
use seems limited
to pre-1980 exposure,
and there appears to be
no link to brain tumors
in either time frame.
As a tragically ironic aside,
while the risk associated with
hair products may have declined
for white men and women,
the opposite trend
seems to have occurred
for certain hair products
targeted towards
African Americans.
The Black Women's Health Study,
which assessed exposure
in the 1990s,
found no association
between breast cancer
and the use of hair "relaxers,"
chemical treatments
used to straighten hair.
But in the early 2000s,
popular straighteners
switched from
non-carcinogenic compounds,
like lye,
to chemical cocktails
containing formaldehyde.
So now,
frequent straightener use
is associated with
about a 30 percent higher
breast cancer risk.
Thankfully, there's been
a shift towards embracing
more natural hair styles in
the African-American community,
resulting in
the sales of hair relaxers
falling by 40 percent
in recent years.
Finally today,
how do you treat the
cause of bad breath?
Bad breath is an
underestimated problem affecting
a significant proportion
of the global population.
It seems most people
regularly report
encountering people
with halitosis.
Masking agents are frequently
used to cover up bad breath,
but studies have shown
that the use
of mouth rinses, sprays,
or mints containing
an agreeable masking odor
only have a short-term effect,
since you're not treating
the underlying cause,
so the exclusive usage
of masking products
can never be truly considered
an effective solution
to the problem.
The cause of bad breath
is oral putrefaction,
the degradation
of certain amino acids
mostly derived
by bacterial breakdown
of proteins in your mouth.
Specifically,
bacteria degrade
the sulfur-containing
amino acids,
such as cysteine
and methionine,
into stinky compounds
like the rotten egg gas
hydrogen sulfide,
so-called
volatile sulfur compounds.
If you measure these compounds
spewing out of people's mouths
with machines
with names like Breathtron,
tooth brushing alone
does not significantly reduce
oral malodor.
Brushing alone reduces
sulfur breath compounds
from more than 450
down to about 300,
but that's still above the
stinky breath threshold of 250.
Add tongue cleaning
and you can drop that down
to right around the threshold,
but adding
an antiseptic mouthwash--
an antibacterial mouthwash--
did even better.
Okay, so what's
the best mouthwash to use?
To find out, researchers used
the cysteine challenge test.
Instead of giving people
dairy products,
which contain
the protein casein,
which is rich in the sulfur
amino acid cysteine,
they just had the participants
swish directly
with some cysteine
and then followed effectiveness
using odor-ograms.
For example, toothbrushing.
When people
swished with cysteine
before brushing their teeth,
here's the spike
in stinky sulfur compounds
spewing out of their mouths.
When they brushed their teeth
with water
and swished again at various
times over the rest of the day,
the spikes pretty much
looked the same,
meaning toothbrushing with water
didn't remove
many bad breath bacteria,
since the subjects were
spewing out similar spikes
starting just 20 minutes later.
Brushing with toothpaste
works better.
See how it knocks down the
next spike of stinky compounds
before the bacteria slowly
grow back throughout the day?
What about using
a tongue scraper?
Tongue scraping knocks it down
by about half
before coming back
over the next few hours.
What about chewing gum?
Some effect that disappears
over the subsequent few hours.
What about various mouthwashes?
First of all,
rinsing with water.
Useless.
Can be helpful
for morning breath,
to rinse any stagnation
that occurred overnight,
but during the day,
just rinsing with water
isn't clearing
many bad breath bacteria.
And swishing
with Scope mouthwash?
Just as useless as water.
Scope is
an anti-bacterial mouthwash
but it must not be good
at killing
the specific bacteria
that cause bad breath.
Peridex, though, cleaned house,
killing off those bacteria
even seven hours later.
What is Peridex?
That's just a brand name
for chlorhexidine.
Chlorhexidine doesn't just get
rid of bad breath bacteria;
it also kills off
the good bacteria on your tongue
that help you make nitric oxide,
which protects your arteries,
and so chlorhexidine can raise
your blood pressure.
And that's not all.
Chlorhexidine
can stain your teeth.
That's not what you want
in a mouthwash.
Adverse effects are not rare.
Tooth staining, the buildup
of tartar, taste disturbance,
and damage to the lining of the
mouth have all been reported
with the use of chlorhexidine
in about 9 out of 10 people.
88 percent of people suffer
various side effects.
But hey, chlorhexidine
may be better
than mouthwashes
with hydrogen peroxide,
which may be carcinogenic,
potentially increasing
your risk of mouth cancer.
That's not just based
on studies on rodents, either.
Cultures of human
mouth lining cells
show significant DNA damage.
Triclosan was another
common antibacterial ingredient
in mouthwashes,
now effectively banned
in over-the-counter products.
Tongue scraping alone
doesn't always resolve
the problem of halitosis.
So, what can we use?
If bad breath persists
after improving tongue
and dental hygiene,
an active zinc-based mouth rinse
can be introduced.
Zinc binds directly to
the volatile sulfur compounds
and prevents them from
gassing out of your mouth.
Mouth rinses containing
ZnCl without alcohol
have been found to instantly
though temporarily
be effective for halitosis.
Researchers looked
at eight mouth rinses,
and the most effective
was a zinc chloride one
and the least effective
was Colgate Plax.
In fact, both of the alcohol
rinses were found to be
the least effective.
The thought is that they
may exacerbate halitosis
by drying up your mouth.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.